So welcome back, everyone.
So on Monday, Tatsu
did an excellent job
of describing a high
level overview of GPUs
and how to think about
performance and all the quirks
that come with GPUs.
This lecture is going to be
a continuation of that, where
we're going to dive more
deeply into the code,
write some Triton kernels, and
as well as do some benchmarking
and profiling.
So just to start,
just to refresh
what's going on
with GPUs, here is
a simplified diagram of what
a typical GPU looks like.
There's memory, and then
the actual GPU chip.
And just to keep in
your head what are
the characteristics of a GPU.
So of course, we're
talking about NVIDIA GPUs,
but Tatsu also talked about
CPUs, and there's AMD and so on.
But focusing on NVIDIA GPUs.
We've had multiple generations,
from A100s, to H100s, to B200s.
And in each generation,
you have a GPU.
It has a number of Streaming
Multiprocessors, or SMs.
And the number of SMs is about
100, between 100 and 200.
So that hasn't really
changed that much.
And then within the individual
SM, there's a set of registers.
So B200s have 65,000 registers
for a total of 256K per SM.
And this also hasn't
changed that much.
In addition, there's a L1
cache as well as shared memory.
So remember, these
are the same memory,
shared memory you can control.
L1, you can't.
This is per SM.
And this is in the same
order ballpark of size.
And then there's L2 cache.
And this is not per SM,
this is for the whole chip.
And this is a bit larger.
And then finally, you have a
High Bandwidth Memory, or HBM,
which is large.
And you see that this
is the number that's
actually going up quite a bit.
OK.
And then in addition
to size, you
can think about what's
happening with the bandwidth.
And essentially, it's
inversely correlated.
So registers are very fast,
L1 is slightly less fast,
L2 is less fast, and high
bandwidth memory is the slowest.
Although eight
terabytes a second
is still not that slow in
the grand scheme of things.
So this is the main hierarchy
you should have in your head.
Large memory is slow
and far but big.
And fast memory like registers
and L1 resides on the SM.
It's local and it's
fast, but small.
OK, that's the environment
we're dealing with.
OK, so then, how do
you program a GPU?
So the program
model is as follows.
So there's notions
of threads, which
each thread executes
a piece of code
on a small part of the data.
So each one of these arrows, you
can think about it as a thread.
These threads are organized
into thread blocks,
also known as Concurrent
Thread Arrays, or CTAs.
And this is a group of threads.
And then finally, you have a
collection of thread blocks
which forms the grid.
So when you launch a
kernel, you're basically
launching a grid of threads and
thread blocks to all parallel
simultaneously do
some computation.
OK, so this is simplified.
There's some other things
that are happening.
For example, there's
H100s and B200s also
have thread block
clusters, which
are clusters of
thread blocks that
enable some amount of
distribution memory.
Also, B200s have tensor memory.
Now for tensor cores, which
is somewhere between registers
and shared memory.
Some of these things are
invisible to the programmer,
but they are in the hardware.
But we won't worry about
them for this intro lecture.
OK, so one thing
you might ask about
is, why do we have
thread blocks?
Why can't we just have
a grid of threads,
and each thread just
takes a piece of data
and does something?
And this would be normally
fine if all you want to do
is element-wise operations,
which we'll see.
For example, GeLU is
an activation function
that applies element-wise.
And threads are pretty natural.
Each thread processes
one element.
So it's like Fi for i equals
ranging over your data set.
But for operations that involve
communicating with threads,
such as softmax or
matrix multiplication,
this view isn't really enough.
And the reason is that,
well, it could be enough
if you were willing to pay the
cost of writing and reading HBM.
Because then you can still
have-- for example, in a matrix
we'll see later, you can just
have every element in a cell.
It goes and computes that
element of the matrix.
And it can just
read and write HBM.
But as we've noticed,
HBM is very slow,
so this would not
be a good strategy.
So instead, what we should
do is use shared memory,
which is local to SM.
And what the thread block
allows you to think about
is a collection of
threads that are all going
to access this shared memory.
So consequently, you can
think about a thread block,
one of these thread
blocks is being scheduled
on one of these semantic--
not semantic, streaming
multiprocessors.
And it does its thing.
And what it's
going to do is it's
going to read a bunch
of data from HBM
and then process it where
the processing might involve
communication between the
threads via the shared memory,
and then writes it back out.
OK.
So this is a critical
piece that comes up.
Later, we'll talk about tiling,
and that's the whole game here.
OK, in Triton, in fact, which
we'll see as a primary way
that we're going to
write kernels these days,
we're going to think
natively in thread blocks.
And I think once you
get the hang of thinking
of thread blocks, this
makes a lot of sense
and makes your life a
lot easier, as we'll see.
OK, so the programming model
is fairly simple, I think.
There's threads, thread
blocks, and grids.
I think things get a
bit more complicated,
is the interaction
between the programming
model and the hardware.
So the programming model
is actually very nice.
It provides abstraction
of the hardware.
When you can write a
kernel, all you have to know
is that there's a
bunch of thread blocks.
You define them and
then define what
computations each thread within
the block or the thread block
has to do.
And those are just writing--
it's like writing Python.
So that part isn't hard.
And in fact, if you
don't care about--
if you just care
about correctness,
that's all you need to know.
But in practice,
the performance is
very sensitive to the hardware.
And so you need to really
deeply understand the hardware
to obtain high performance.
And in fact, the
whole reason we're
talking about GPUs
and kernels is
that you're trying to
squeeze out performance.
So there's these two
levels here where
you're trying to
understand the computation,
and that is only a part
of the programming model.
But how fast it runs
is going to be strongly
dependent on the hardware.
OK, so I'm going to give you
some examples of why this
matters, and some of
this will be review
from what Tatsu talked about.
But hopefully it will reinforce
some of these concepts.
So I think there will be
around five different examples.
And this is just to give you a
flavor of the considerations.
So there's something
called warps,
which I didn't talk about.
So in the very
simplified view, warps
are not really part of this
clean picture of the programming
model.
You have threads and
thread blocks or grids.
Technically, you can
also exceed the warps,
but you don't have to when
you're just programming.
So what is a warp?
So each thread blocks, remember,
is a collection of threads.
But these threads are
actually grouped into warps.
And there's basically
32 threads per warp.
So for example, if you have
64 threads in a thread block,
there's two warps, the
first 32 and the second 32.
And as Tatsu
mentioned last time,
all threads within a warp,
all of these T's, must
execute the same instruction
in lockstep on SM.
So every cycle,
they have to execute
exactly the same instruction.
And control divergence is when
different threads within a warp
need to actually execute
different instructions.
For example, if you have
branching, if something,
then A else B.
And then what happens
is that you can only
do the A's in your
threads in your warp,
and then you do the B.
So this gets sequential.
So this is bad and
inefficient, and that's
why branching is something
you want to generally avoid.
One thing that's, I think,
really cool about warps
is that a SM actually is
running multiple warps.
There's a warp
scheduler, and there's
a bunch of resident warps
that are about to run.
Each warp has some--
threads have registers.
And the SM can switch
between them with zero cost.
Right, this is not true
in general, like on a CPU.
But this way that it's
designed is to hide latency.
So this is important,
because one
of the warps is, for
example, reading from HBM,
which remember is
very expensive,
can take 100 cycles
or something.
You don't want to just sit
around waiting for that warp
to do nothing.
You switch immediately
to another warp
where it can actually do
some tensor core operations.
OK, so that's one thing
to note about the warp.
And another reason
why warp comes up
is this idea of occupancy.
More specifically,
warp occupancy.
So each thread, just
the hardware constraint
says that each thread can
use at most 255 registers.
OK, and so what happens
is that the SM has
a fixed number of registers.
So the more registers
each thread is using,
the fewer threads you can have.
That's just math.
And that can reduce
your occupancy.
But that's not necessarily
bad, because if you
have fewer threads.
But each thread is doing more
work, that can actually be good.
So occupancy is something
that you can measure,
but it's not necessarily
the larger, the better.
Because there are some
other tradeoffs here.
And in fact, an
example where you
might want to have fewer
threads is this idea
of thread coarsening,
where let's say
you have an
element-wise operation
and you can have one thread just
perform work on one element.
OK, so then you have
a lot of threads.
But you can also say each thread
processes multiple elements.
Like a constant, maybe eight.
So that gives you
fewer threads, which
makes scheduling and
these things easier,
but each thread is
doing more work.
So if your threads
are very light,
maybe you want to fatten
them up a little bit.
OK.
So just as an example of
what might happen here.
So suppose you have a
block, a thread block
with 128 threads in it.
And each thread is
using 160 registers.
OK.
So there's a
hardware constraint.
So the B200s have maximum of
registers of 65,000 per SM.
And it also has
a constraint that
says you can't run more
than 64 warps at a time.
So then you can go and
do some simple math
to compute what is
the occupancy here.
So number of
registers per thread.
This has to be less than 255.
That's fine.
The number of registers
that you're using per block
is the number of
threads per block
times the number of
registers per thread.
That's about 20,000.
That means you can run at
most three blocks on your SM
concurrently.
And then that
corresponds to 12 warps.
And because the number
of maximum warps is 64,
that means you have
an occupancy of 18%.
So we're only running 18% the
total number of warps you have.
And this is because you have a
lot of registers use per thread.
OK, so this is an example of
where I guess this is memory,
is constraining you in terms
of how much compute you can do.
OK, here's another example.
Something called bank conflicts.
This applies to shared memory.
So remember, shared
memory is like L1.
It's on an SM.
And just the way
the hardware works
is that shared memory is divided
into 32 banks, each one four
bytes wide.
OK, so these are my 32 banks,
and this is my memory here.
Each bank has many
elements here.
So there's a constraint
that says every clock cycle,
each bank can only be accessed
by one thread, at most
one thread.
Assuming that's not a location.
So for example, if
you can't access
this location and this
location at the same time.
Which means that if you
have multiple threads that
are trying to access
the same bank,
the accesses have
to be serialized.
And this is called
a bank conflict.
In the worst case
example, imagine
this were a matrix that
was laid out like this.
And you had some operation where
32 threads, you think, wow,
this 32 is so great.
I can massively
parallelize this,
and you try to all
access this first column.
They're just going
to just wait in line.
And this is a 32-way
bank conflict,
which is the worst possible
setting you can be in.
Now you could say, well,
OK, why did you do that?
Just like access
rows, of course.
But this is unavoidable,
because, for example,
if you're doing a
matmul, you have
to access rows of one matrix
and columns of another matrix.
And sometimes you do
transposes, so you can't always
just get away with choosing
the order in which you go down.
For element-wise
operations, it's fine.
You can go in any order.
But if you're doing
matmuls, you can't
control for every matrix
which row major or column
major you're doing.
There are some solutions
here, which I won't get into.
Something called swizzling,
which arranges your shared
memory so that when
you're going through,
you can avoid bank conflicts.
OK, so that's another
consideration.
And when you're profiling, you
can look at the bank conflicts,
you can look at occupancy.
And you can see
what's happening.
A final note which--
actually, two more things.
So memory coalescing,
which you talked about.
So I'll just really
quickly remind
people what this is about.
So when you have 32 threads in a
warp and they try to access HBM,
the memory accesses
actually get combined
into a transaction of 128 bytes,
which are called cache lines.
And it goes and
fetches it all at once.
So imagine you have
memory laid out like this.
This is 32.
And in the best case, which
is called full coalescing,
all the threads are accessing
the same cache line.
So you have thread 1 accessing
M00, thread 2 accessing M01,
and so on.
Which means that
all at once, you're
going to grab this
entire cache line.
Right, and whereas if
you go down the columns,
then you're going to
fetch a lot of memory
here, which you're
not going to use.
Same for the second
row and so on.
And so this feels similar
to bank conflicts,
but it's a very
different constraint.
And this is about shared
memory, and this is about HBM.
OK.
OK, so final thing,
block occupancy.
So thread blocks are,
remember, scheduled onto SMS.
But we live in a finite--
logically, you can define as
many thread blocks as you want.
But physically on chip, you only
have a certain number of SMs.
For example, 148.
So if you launch
160 thread blocks,
then you can only
schedule 148 of them.
And then you have to
wait until they're done,
and then you schedule the 12.
But what happens
if you schedule 12
is that there's a bunch of SMs
are just not doing anything.
So that's called low occupancy.
When the last wave
of thread blocks
gets fewer than the total
maximum number of thread blocks.
OK, so in general,
maybe it's a good idea
to make the number of thread
blocks divide the SMs.
So maybe just to
summarize here, there
is a very elegant
programming model
where you have a
grid of thread blocks
and the thread blocks have
individual threads in them.
And in terms of the memory,
HBM is global to everyone.
Shared memory is local
to a thread block.
And registers are
local to a thread.
But again, all the details
of the hardware-- warps,
bank conflicts, memory
coalescing, occupancy--
really determine performance.
And many of these details are
hard to know, because, I mean,
the profiling tells you
a bunch of information.
But you have to know
exactly how many SMs there
are and exactly the
sizing of everything.
Sometimes the scheduler
does something
you don't really have
control over what it's doing.
So it's a little messier
than the programming model.
OK, I will stop
there for questions.
Yeah?
Yes, a quick question.
So Cam, is there a
scenario in which you
one can share with them
or-- like, for example,
in the problem that we see 140
SM [INAUDIBLE] blocks, right.
And we have to launch
into two different ways.
Is there no way in which
a block can share an SM?
Yeah, so the question is,
can a block share an SM?
I think the issue is if you're
doing things right, then the--
I guess it depends on the block.
If you have a block
that's for example,
using most of the
tensor cores on the SM,
then putting another
block there isn't really
going to speed things up.
I think fundamentally,
there is this jagged problem
here of unevenness.
Because the blocks
have to stay together.
So you can't take this and
spread it out over here.
The thing you would do is
to change your blocksize.
So you change the
number of blocks
so you don't get this tail here.
Any other questions?
OK, so let's move on.
Hopefully you guys are getting
more comfortable with GPUs now.
So now I'm going to talk about
benchmarking and profiling.
I'm not going to
actually maybe say
that much in terms of content.
But I do want to emphasize
the philosophy here, which is,
here's a recipe for success.
You benchmark and
profile your code.
You make changes, and you
benchmark your profile,
your code again.
And the reason I'm doing
benchmarking and profiling
as opposed to teaching
you try and earlier
is because you should
always just measure
what's going on in your
code and figure out
what the bottlenecks are before
you start writing kernels.
OK, so benchmarking is
basically how long things take.
And it gives you just
this end to end time.
It doesn't tell you
where things are spent.
But nonetheless, it's pretty
useful, because ultimately,
that's the thing that you
care about, how long things
are running for.
And it also gives you,
because it distills things
into one number, you can see how
things are scaling, let's say,
with dimension.
So there's a nice
tool for benchmarking.
But because this class is
language models from scratch,
I'm going to do it from scratch.
But I think I'm doing it just
to highlight a few gotchas
with benchmarking.
So let's say we have
this operation, matrix
multiplication.
So run operation 2 is this
wrapper that basically
instantiates two random square
matrices of size dimension
by dimension.
And then it returns a function
to perform the operation.
OK, so matmul, if you
call this, basically
does the matmul of those
two random matrices.
OK, the random
matrices are generated,
it's just like
multiplying the two.
OK, so how do you benchmark?
So the naive thing to do
is just start time, run it,
and then stop time.
But there's a few things.
One is that always remember
to do your warm-up.
I think I mentioned this
on the second lecture,
but I think it's
worth emphasizing.
And this is because if you have
some things are lazily compiled
and you want to just make
sure that that thing is--
that time doesn't factor into.
Because most of
the time, you care
about how fast something
is, because you're
going to run it
over and over again,
so the initial conditions
don't really matter.
And then you often want
to time it multiple times
because there is some variance.
The proper way to time things is
to use these CUDA events that--
a start event and an end event,
which you can call record on.
Actually do the computation and
then hit the end event record.
And then remember to synchronize
to wait for the CUDA threads
to finish, because
everything on the GPU
is happening if
you have an async.
And this is a
synchronization barrier.
And then you record the time.
OK, and then you can do
this again, and then again.
And then here, we're
just taking the average.
If you are being
very particular,
you probably want to maybe
look at the whole distribution,
the P95 or whatever.
But we'll just do
the average here.
And then one thing that you can
do with benchmarking is you can,
let's say, scale
up your matrices
and see how the time changes.
And you can see that in this
case, matrix multiplication, as
expected, it should
grow cubically.
But notice that there is this
flaw where up until you get up
to almost 2,000
dimensional matrices,
things are basically a constant.
Right, and this is because,
as we've discussed,
the shapes of these GPUs are
built for fairly large matrix
multiplications.
And if you have a
2 by 2 matrix, it's
going to be very inefficient.
OK.
So really quickly on profiling.
Profiling tells you where
time is actually spent.
Hopefully all of you are
familiar with profiling
and are doing it.
Maybe less obviously,
profiling, even
if you don't care
about the time,
helps you figure
out what's actually
happening under the hood.
Because especially with
these high level languages,
you write some code, and then
it runs and you get some result.
And sometimes it can be
just good to understand
what's actually going on.
So PyTorch has a
built-in profiler.
In your assignment,
you'll use Nsight,
which gives you more details.
But we're going to skip that
in the interest of time.
So let's start with just if you
add two numbers and-- or sorry,
two tensors in
PyTorch, again, a run
operation creates
two random matrices
and applies the operation.
So in profiling, I'm warming up.
And then I'm just putting this
context of-- the profiling
context and doing the run.
And then let's look at what the
profile looks like for just a
plus b in PyTorch.
Normally doing PyTorch, you
probably don't think about it.
It's like, OK, well, these
two tensors just get added.
So what's actually going
on underneath the hood?
Right, so if you look at the
things that it's calling,
there is this long name,
kernel at CUDA functor add.
So this is basically a
kernel that adds to tensors.
And the times aren't going
to be that interesting,
because I'm only adding.
So that's going to
take 100% of the time.
But this tells you that,
well, underneath the hood
there is this thing called add.
What about matmul?
In PyTorch, I'm doing a at b.
Similarly, there
is this long name
that describes this
particular matmul kernel.
Cutlass f32, f32,
64x64x16, and so on.
Notice that if you
change the dimensions--
so now I'm doing a
128 by 128 matmul--
you get actually
a different one.
If you look closely, that this
is 64x64x16, this is 32x32x16.
OK, so underneath
the hood, PyTorch,
it looks like you're
doing just at.
But underneath the hood,
there could be all sorts
of things that are happening.
So observations.
Here, you can see which
CUDA kernels are actually
being called.
These are generally the ones
that have the long names.
And different CUDA kernels
are invoked depending
on the tensor dimensions.
The name actually
tells you something
about the
implementation as well.
So this name.
So cutlass is the NVIDIA CUDA
library for linear algebra.
SM100 corresponds to the
Blackwell architecture.
So this is a kernel
that's specifically
designed for Blackwell.
This is f32.
And then 64x64x16 is
the shape of the tile,
which we're going to talk about
later when we talk about tiling
in the context of matmuls.
OK, so that's
benchmarking profiling.
Just remember to do it.
I think we make you do
it on the assignment,
so you have no choice.
OK.
So let's apply this to another
example here on the GeLU.
So remember, the GeLU
activation function
is this function, which is a
typical non-linearity that's
used.
Often, it's approximated with
this tanh approximation, which
is more computer friendly.
OK, so naively, if you
implement the GeLU,
you can do it in
PyTorch just like this.
So you take a tensor, you
just take this equation
and you just put it
into PyTorch, OK.
That's fine.
And you get some number.
PyTorch also has a built in.
If you call functional GeLU, you
can get that version as well.
And you can check
that they're the same.
You can run the
two GeLU versions
and make sure that the answer
is the same for a random input.
There's also something that
people probably have discovered.
If you haven't
encountered this, this
is an important thing to know.
Is that you can take
any PyTorch function,
you call torch.compile
on it, and it
generates another function.
And it does the same thing.
OK, so we have three
horses in this race.
We have the naive
implementation.
We have the built-in
We have the compiled
implementation.
So we can benchmark them.
Naive takes three.
I guess this is 3.75.
Built-in is much
faster and compiled
is much faster as well, but
not maybe as quite as fast
as built-in.
OK.
So what's happening here?
Why are these things different?
They all compute
the same answer,
but they have wildly different
performance characteristics.
And so here we can
pull up the profiler
and see what's actually
going on underneath the hood.
So if you look at the
naive GeLU here and just do
a profile, this--
something's wrong
with this view,
so I'm going to go to this.
So you see that the profile
shows how time is being spent.
There's a bunch of different
kernels on this binary functor
unary add.
tanh is a kernel here.
And this corresponds to the
fact that in PyTorch, when
we write the PyTorch
expression, you
look at the
computation graph, and
each primitive in
the computation
graph is actually
realized in the kernel.
Right.
And the reason this is slow is
that when you launch a kernel,
the kernel has to read from HBM.
Pull it all the way over to
your SM, do the computation,
and write it back.
And then the kernel
picks that up from HBM
and then writes it back,
and so on and so forth.
So you're doing a lot of reads
and writes back and forth.
Because between
kernel invocations,
things have to go back to HBM.
So if you look at what
the built-in is doing,
this is actually not
that interesting.
There's this GeLU CUDA
kernel implementation,
which is a single kernel that
just implements the GeLU.
And so why does this exist?
Well, because people use GeLU.
So someone wrote a
kernel for it and put it
in the standard library.
I mean, there's nothing magical.
So compilation is
really interesting here.
I'm not going to say too
much about how it works,
but it's really, I think,
a fascinating topic where
you can take a naive
implementation, which, remember,
it's in PyTorch, it has
a computation graph.
And run a compiler.
Which basically, if you look
at what's underneath the hood,
it's just a single kernel.
And this is because
it's figured out
to look at the computation
graph and essentially write
that kernel in Triton.
So you can see that this is
actually a Triton kernel.
OK, so naive implementation.
Multiple kernels requires
multiple reads and writes
to and from HBM.
There's no kernel fusion here.
This is slow.
The built-in compiler
version, there's one kernel.
Basically all the
operation in the GeLU
have been fused together
into one kernel.
So you read from HBM once, you
write to HBM once per element.
And you see that the compiled
kernel is a Triton kernel.
OK, so that maybe
is a good segue
to talk about what this
Triton thing is all about.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Let's see.
I mean, I guess it says
CUDA kernel implementation,
so I imagine someone
wrote it in CUDA.
OK, any other questions?
Yeah?
Why is Triton kernel
faster than this one?
So why is the Triton
kernel faster?
So a Triton kernel is actually
not faster in this case.
Oh, sorry.
The compiled kernel
is one Triton kernel,
and this is slower
than the built-in.
Yeah.
I think last year when I did
this, it was actually closer.
But these things change, and
it's very hardware dependent.
And I think none of this
is terribly optimized.
This is just giving you
the general idea here.
OK, so let's write
some Triton kernels.
So remember our
programming model.
You have a bunch of threads
organized by Thread groups,
a thread blocks, and there's
a grid of thread blocks.
And if you were to write in
CUDA, which was originally
developed by NVIDIA, and
that's been for years the thing
that you do when
you write kernels,
the mental model is,
what does each thread do?
So you write a piece of
code which essentially
has some ID that
identifies which
thread you're talking about,
and it just executes the code.
So the nice thing about this is
that it's very closely related
to what is actually happening
underneath the hood.
And it's fine-grained, gives
you fine-grained control.
But there's cons here,
which is that, remember,
all these threads are
in a thread block.
And some operations require
them to communicate.
So what has to happen is that
they have to synchronize.
And they read from
HBM all at once.
And they have to synchronize
and do the computation.
And you have to basically
do that bookkeeping.
So if you were doing all
element-wise operations,
this CUDA is just fine.
It doesn't really matter.
But as you get more
complex operations,
then try and provide some
value of the abstraction.
So Triton was
developed by OpenAI.
I think by now, it's
been pretty standard.
You basically specify what
each thread block does.
Generally it's powerful enough,
especially for this class
that you're getting started.
If you really go and want to
exploit every single new feature
of the latest
hardware, it might not
give you the full flexibility.
But let's not worry about that.
And the conceptual framework
to think about in Triton
is that you're thinking
about, what does a block do?
A block is going to load
data into shared memory,
operate it on, and write
it back to global memory.
So in some sense, these
blocks are intermediate point
between thinking about what
individual elements are doing
as well as thinking about
the general operation.
And so in PyTorch, you basically
define these huge matrices
and you say multiply
them together.
And that's the atomic operation.
And a lot of what
you're thinking about
is, how do I get things
into big matmuls?
Right, and at some
level, Triton is
a hybrid between that and
the individual elements,
as we'll see.
OK, so let's start with
the GeLU example here.
So let's define an 8,000
dimensional vector and start
writing some Triton.
OK, so Triton is basically
going to be you write Python.
How many of you have
written Triton before?
Just a show of hands.
OK, OK.
Not that many, which is good,
because then you won't be bored.
OK, so this is normal PyTorch.
Right, there's no Triton here.
But I'm just preparing.
And so what I'm going to
do is I take this tensor,
and I'm going to allocate
an output tensor.
OK, because in Triton, we're not
thinking functionally anymore.
We're just thinking
about moving.
You have to explicitly
read and write.
So there's no returning value.
So I'm going to
allocate the output
tensor, which I'm going to--
the kernel's going to write to.
And then so this tensor can
be arbitrarily big, right.
And I can't generally
fit this all into one SM,
because it's just too big.
So I need to break
it up into blocks.
So what I'm going to do is
you can think about this x
as being this array.
I'm going to chop
it up into blocks.
So the total number
of elements is 8,000.
I'm just going to set the
blocksize to 1,024 for now.
And then I have eight blocks.
OK.
So then I'm going to use this
weird syntax to call the kernel.
So Triton GeLU kernel.
This basically in brackets
tells me essentially the shape
of the grid.
So basically, this says
the grid has num blocks.
Blocks.
And I'm going to, for
every one of these blocks,
invoke this function,
Triton GeLU kernel, which
I'll talk about in a bit.
I'm going to pass in an x, y
num elements and the blocksize.
OK.
All right, so
unfortunately, I'm not
going to be able to
trace through this,
so I'll just show you what
the code looks like here.
So let me get rid of that.
OK, so this is probably the
simplest kernel you can imagine.
So when you are looking
at the triton gelu kernel,
now this is before
we had x and y.
So now these are pointers.
Right, you can think about
these as just integers,
they're addresses.
So you have to get
comfortable with that.
And then we have the number
of elements and the blocksize,
which are basically actually
passed in from here.
OK, so the way to think about
it is that for every block,
we're going to have this
function being called.
And what happens is the
first thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to wake up.
This block wakes up
and say, who am I?
Well, the program
ID is-- basically
the PID is basically
identifying the block.
So PID would be 0 for this
block 1, 2, and 3 here.
OK, so now I have to
figure out what data
I'm going to operate on.
So that's PID times blocksize.
So this is the offset
into x pointer.
So if PID is 0, then start is 0.
If PID is 1, then
start is blocksize.
If PID is 2, then it's 2
times blocksize, and so on.
OK.
So now, I'm going to figure
out the span I'm operating on.
So offsets is start plus.
This is the Triton library.
A range 0 blocksize, which
conceptually gives you
the integers 0 through
blocksize minus 1.
So offsets is going
to be essentially
for-- let's say
block 1, it's going
to be blocksize blocksize
plus 1 all the way to blocks
2 times blocksize minus 1.
OK, so in this case, num
elements divides by blocksize.
But in general,
that's not the case.
So you'll often see in train
code, there's this masking.
Which says, well, sometimes if
the-- let's say the tensor only
goes up to here.
Then I'm going to
form a mask, which
is going to be true
up until that point
and false after that point.
And for blocks that are
not the final block,
it's going to be just all ones.
OK, so now I've done the setup.
What I do is I read.
And this is basically
pointer arithmetic.
So x pointer, remember,
is the integer
that specifies the memory
location of where x is.
I'm going to add
offsets to that,
which gives me the first
blocksize number of elements
there.
According to the mask,
if I'm masked out,
then I don't read it.
And then now I think you can
just think about this a vector.
And then you do your
normal computation.
And then you get y.
And y is the same size as x.
And then you do
tl store y pointer
plus offsets y and the mask.
OK, so this load loads
from HBM, does some stuff,
and then it writes back to HBM.
OK, I'm going to stop there
and take any questions
about this first Triton kernel.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So the difference is, what is
the difference between CUDA?
And for this element wise, it
looks pretty much the same,
right.
And in fact, CUDA is
even, I think, simpler,
because it really
is element wise.
You wake up, and you
identify the thread.
And then you just
operate on that element.
Now the only thing
here is that it's
like the vectorized version,
where you have a block
and you operate on that block.
Later, we'll see that
operating on blocks
is doing more than-- if
you do something more
than element-wise,
then CUDA is going
to be a lot more
annoying to work with.
So a bunch of questions.
Yeah, back there.
How does this relate to if you
wanted to use the tensor units?
So how is this related to if you
want to use the tensor units?
So I'll later show you
what this code actually
compiles down into.
And maybe I'll get back to that.
But the short answer is
that you don't control that.
The hardware figures
out where to put things.
Yeah?
Can you actually
walk through what's
happening at tf.load from
HBM to share to register?
What's the step by step where
data is actually flowing?
Yeah, so the question is, what
is actually happening when
this statement is executed?
So the short version is that
this is in some sense a lie.
Right, it's not like
the GPU actually
calls the Triton
library on the GPU
and it's actually
executing this code.
This is basically
for our consumption
to specify the computation.
The compiler takes this,
as we'll see later,
and writes it into
something called ptx,
and then it will
actually do the work.
So that's mechanically
what's happening,
which I'll get to later.
If you're asking about
the conceptual question,
the way to think about
this is that this--
x pointer is a memory
location in HBM.
And this basically specifies
a range of memory locations.
And load takes those
memory locations
and returns the data
associated with them.
Here, I have a local
variable called x.
In practice, this is
going to be generally
a register or shared memory.
Triton figures out
what to do there.
[INAUDIBLE]
--at the threat level.
When this is invoked,
it's not really clear.
Did I line up what is
going to be in shared
and going to be at the
register level beforehand,
or is it happening
now, which is way late?
And so then so that's
just where all the threads
are sitting idle to get
a memory to flush in.
I'm sure it's ready to
execute so that we're not
sitting there
twiddling our thumbs,
just waiting for data
to come in from HBM.
Yeah, yeah.
So the question is, when does
this actually get executed,
and doesn't this block?
Let me try to come
back to this question
when I show you the ptx,
and maybe hopefully it
will provide a bit more
context on what's happening.
OK, any other questions?
OK, so all the kernels are going
to look something like this.
So I do want to make
sure people understand
just the general form, which
is that you have generally
your inputs, your outputs.
You wake up, you
figure out which
index you're going to look at.
You read.
You do some stuff, and
then you write to HBM.
OK.
So let's talk about ptx briefly.
So let's see, does this work?
Does this link work?
OK, so when you write
Triton, the compiler
generates ptx code, which is
this intermediate assembly
language for GPUs.
I am obviously not going
to go through all of this,
but just to give you the
flavor of what this looks like.
Let me actually start
with the observation.
So a few things.
So this is now what a
thread is actually doing.
Not a thread block, because
that's been compiled away.
And so if you look at--
a few notes here.
So this LD global is
basically saying load from HBM
into some registers.
And the registers are denoted as
the r are integer registers, fr,
floating point registers.
And then you have statements
like mov 0 into r5,
mov 0 into r6, and so on.
And then you have
multiplication.
You're going to multiply this
register by this constant
and then put it into this.
So this code gets executed.
And at the bottom, you
should see global store.
So this is writing
back into the HBM.
So this gets executed.
This is actually the code that
gets executed on a thread.
And Triton is basically
a layer up above that.
One other thing to notice is
that you see all these blocks
and what's going on there.
And what's going on
there is I alluded
to thread coarsening, which
is that this is one thread.
But rather than processing
a single element,
it's actually processing
eight elements.
So the compiler decided that,
well, actually, this thread
is pretty lightweight.
It doesn't do that
much, so let's just
try to thicken it
up a little bit.
So looking at ptx can give you
some of appreciation for what's
going on underneath the hood.
Yeah?
So it makes this for
each individual--
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, does it
make this for each thread?
So this is compiled once.
And it's the same piece of
code that each thread runs.
And the way that the
thread distinguishes
itself is that this
piece of code gets
passed basically the thread ID.
So here, the cta.x
is the block index,
and tid.x is the thread index.
So this basically, if this
piece of code is running,
this tells you
which block I'm in.
And tid.x tells you which
thread inside that block I'm in.
OK.
Any other questions?
And I'm trying to
figure out how to--
OK.
OK, so that's generally a flavor
of your first Triton kernel
load from HBM compute
right back to HBM.
And then we saw the ptx, which
is the grungy what actually
happens underneath the hood.
There's still a lot of things
that are not specified in ptx.
Like, for example, which
SM things are operating on
and the warps and everything.
A lot of those are
hardware controlled,
so you don't even see.
Yeah?
So ptx code is generated by
the compiler, not something
that you would normally code?
It looks like it's
assembly code.
Yeah, so the question is, is ptx
just generated by the compiler?
So there are people
who do write ptx
if you really think you're
better than the compiler.
And I think the NVIDIA compilers
are generally pretty mature,
but some other accelerators
that are less developed.
I think sometimes you
just have to reach in
and actually
handhold a bit more.
But generally, yeah, you
shouldn't need to do that.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
My work will get
scheduled onto an SM.
I'll get to that
tf.load and it's almost
like a CPU trap call
where I'm just waiting
for something to happen.
And now I am turning my
thumbs and some other work
will get scheduled over me.
And then it will do operations.
Now that you have
to upload is done,
then I'll reschedule that work
and then I'll continue on.
Is that--
Yeah, that's right.
So just to repeat the
question or the comment.
So if you look at
this triangle code,
these statements,
this load, is going
to block for some
number of cycles.
And then so this is
running on some thread
on some warp on some SM.
And remember, the SM is running
multiple warps at the same time.
So when you get
to that point, it
can just find
another warp to run.
And then when this is
done, the warp scheduler
comes back and takes over.
Why do you [INAUDIBLE]?
Sorry.
Oh, sorry.
I recall from [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, so the question is,
why four warp schedules?
I don't exactly the
reason behind that.
OK, so now let's go through
some other examples.
Maybe just as a quick preview.
We're going to do
three more examples.
GeLU is the simplest form.
Even though the computation
has a lot of messiness.
It's just element wise.
So conceptually, in the
context of this lecture,
is actually very simple.
Now we're going to look at
Softmax, where now you're
going to have to do reduction.
But in this case, we're
going to think about the case
where row fits on a block.
And then we're going to
consider the case where
row doesn't fit on a
block, and then we're
going to do go up to matmul.
And then hopefully
by that point,
you'll have all the
ingredients that you
need to do the assignment and
implement flash attention.
OK.
So so far, we looked at
element wise operations.
Now let's think about
other operations
that aggregate over
multiple values.
So remember what
the Softmax does.
Let's just think of as a matrix.
You exponentiate and normalize
each row of a matrix.
OK, so this is used in intention
and used in generating output
probabilities.
Generally a good thing to do.
So let's just start with
a naive implementation
and just keep track
of what's happening.
So here, I'm
defining this tensor.
And here's the naive
implementation.
Actually, I think this
is on assignment one.
OK, anyway.
So here, I have
an M by N matrix.
And so I need to, for
every row, compute the--
I'm going to compute
the max of each row.
And this is for
numerical stability.
I'm going to
subtract off the max.
And then I'm going to
exponentiate element-wise.
And I'm going to sum and
compute the normalization
constant for every row.
And I'm going to divide.
And then that's it.
OK.
So if you count the number of
reads and writes, remember,
this is just plain PyTorch.
So this is a different kernel.
This is a different kernel.
And unless you call
to torch and compile,
these are going to be
different operations.
And each operation is going
to read and write, read
and write from HBM.
OK, so you have five MN
reads, three MN writes.
And in principle, you should
really only have much fewer.
OK, so this is a piece of code.
Makes sense.
Everyone should be familiar
what the Softmax is doing.
OK.
So let's write down
the Triton kernel.
And in some sense, the form
is going to be very similar.
Just like in the GeLU.
Right, once you do
the scaffolding,
the core computation looks very
much like the naive version.
So what we're going
to do is we're going
to say each row is a block.
OK.
And why do I make
each row a block?
Well, because now,
remember, each row,
I have to normalize and sum.
So it's not element-wise.
So Softmax is not
an element wise.
But it is row wise.
So the blocks don't interact.
And the blocks don't have
shared memory, so that's fine.
There's no shared
memory across blocks.
So then within each row, I'm
just going to do some stuff.
OK, so let's see what happens.
So again, I'm going
to, in Python,
I'm going to allocate
my output tensor.
I have this M by N matrix.
I'm going to define the
blocksize as basically
the number of columns.
Go to the next power
of 2 for good luck.
And then the number of blocks
is just the number of rows.
OK, and I'm going
to call this kernel.
So how many blocks are there?
M.
M. Right, one for each row.
And each block, I'm going
to pass the input pointer,
the output pointer.
And then I'm going to also
pass these strides which
tell me how far to move down.
OK, let me actually go and show
you that Softmax kernel, OK.
OK, so what does
this look like here?
So I wake up.
I'm on a particular row, OK.
And this is going to give
me all the columns from 0
to the number of blocksize,
which I'm assuming
that's all the columns.
I'm going to read.
So basically, I need to figure
out where to read from memory,
and that's going to be
the start of my data.
Plus which row.
And the row stride
basically gives me
every row is-- basically,
this is the number of columns,
essentially.
It's going to tell me
where how far to go down.
And then this is x pointers
is basically the addresses
of all the data I need to load.
I load them up.
And here, I do this thing
where if it's masked out, then
I put minus infinity,
because that's
going to be the equivalent of
a 0 for the Softmax operation.
And then this part is
essentially the same
as the naive Softmax.
I'm just going to
compute the max,
subtract it off,
exponentiate, sum, and divide.
And then I write it back.
OK.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so this is the version
where each block can just
span the entire row.
And you can see that Triton
makes this very easy, right.
Because this is as if you
were just writing normal
PyTorch code.
So if everything fits in
a block, you basically--
the thing is, if you
can fit it into a block,
you can just write
normal PyTorch, almost.
Yeah?
What if my number of
columns, the number of rows,
are bigger than blocksize?
Yeah, so we'll get to that.
Now the number of
columns, rows, in general,
it's going to be much
larger than the blocksize.
So we'll come back
to that, yeah.
So if you wanted to do
a Softmax per column,
do you have to do [INAUDIBLE]?
So the question is if you
want to do Softmax by column.
I think that should be
fine, because here, we're
tracking these pointers, right.
So the pointers can be anything.
Basically, I think all
you would have to do
is change the stride here to
basically access the columns.
Actually, it would be here.
The column offsets, you
would just multiply this
by the row stride, I think.
OK, let's move on.
All right, so now,
warming up to the matmul.
Suppose that your row
doesn't fit into a block.
OK, so what do you
do in this case?
So for example, if
you have, let's say,
a row that's 4,000 columns, but
the blocksize is only 1,024.
So you have to do
something here.
So here's the strategy.
We're going to break
up the row into tiles.
So in this case, there's
going to be four tiles.
And each thread is going
to iterate over the tiles
and accumulate a sum.
And then finally
at the end, we're
going to do the reduction
by summing everything
that each thread produced.
So I'll show you
an example of this.
And now I'm switching
from Softmax
to row sum because it's
just easier to think about.
OK, so here, OK, well, this
is not very interesting.
The built-in row sum does
what you would expect.
So the row sum operation
just basically takes a matrix
and then computes the
sum of each row, OK.
So just no surprises there.
OK, so conceptually what we're
going to do here is as follows.
OK, so each block is still
in charge of one row.
So that part hasn't changed.
So suppose block one, row one.
I wake up, and what do I do?
I'm going to remember,
now, there's tiles.
And suppose tile 0 is
columns 0 through 3,
tile 1 is columns 4 through 7.
And then tile 2 is
columns 8 through 11.
OK, so what I'm
going to do here is
that I'm going to iterate now.
So first, I basically process
this, all the threads.
Basically, each thread
keeps a kind of accumulator
and processes the first tile.
And it's going to move
on to the next tile,
and it's going to add
the current element
to the accumulator.
So here, I'm putting 3, 1, 4, 1.
And then the second
loop iteration,
I'm going to add 5 to this.
I get 8.
I add 9 to this, I get 10.
2 to 4, and 6 to 1, right.
So each of these
four threads is going
to be accumulating
its own thing.
And then at the end, I
do another for tile 2.
I add 5 and 3 to the
respective accumulators.
So at the end of the day, I have
this, a vector of accumulators.
And then that is actually--
that, I can just sum up.
OK, so let's see what
the code looks like here.
So I'm just going to
call the row sum kernel.
And let's see.
OK, so here's what
it looks like.
So wake up.
I am on a particular row.
And this is what
one row looks like.
There's one tile, a second
tile, a third tile, and so on.
So n is the number of
elements of that row.
And blocksize is the
size of this tile.
OK.
So remember, blocksize
is the number of threads.
I'm processing more data than
the larger than the blocksize.
I just have to do
it iteratively now.
So I'm going to loop
over all of the tiles.
So start is going to
go from 0 to blocksize
to 2 times blocksize,
and so on and so forth.
So each time I'm jumping
across, I am doing calls.
Basically get the offsets
at the particular tile.
And then I'm going to
load the data from HBM,
and I'm going to add
it to the accumulation.
So this accumulation is going to
be either in registers or shared
memory.
OK.
And then finally after I
loop over all the tiles,
I process the whole
row, I get basically--
for every thread I have
accumulator of what
that thread has picked up.
And I can just do a sum to get
a scalar, and I write it out.
OK, so this is a little bit
more complicated than before,
because now we have a
for loop within a thread.
And this is necessary when your
data doesn't fit within a block.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Just in case we don't
have enough register.
We have to put it in--
Yeah, so the question is
I think if you can control
where the accumulator resides.
At least in this Triton program,
you don't explicitly say.
And this is up to
the Triton compiler
to figure out where to put it.
But in general, if the
blocksize is large enough,
it has to go in shared memory.
OK.
All right, does this make sense?
Just to, I think, make sure
people are on the same page.
Remember when GeLU,
we also split a row
into a bunch of pieces.
But those were blocks.
Right, and so each
of those pieces
was a block that was
processed independently.
These are not blocks.
These are tiles.
The block corresponds
to this whole row.
And the block has to basically
process all the tiles.
And so this is where it starts
to not look like PyTorch,
because you're not
able to process all
your data in one nice kind of--
not everything fits
into shared memory.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
--also stored in shared memory?
Yeah.
Let's say the accumulator
is stored in shared memory.
Yeah.
OK.
All right, so let's
now maybe go on
to our finale, which is matmul.
OK, so matmul, of course,
is the bread and butter
of deep learning.
It's been optimized to death.
And it's, in some sense,
very fundamental operation.
So you take two matrices,
you multiply them.
I'm going to add a little
bit of a twist here.
I'm going to do a matmul
followed by a ReLU,
just because, just for kicks.
OK.
Well, this happens, right.
Because if you have one
linear layer, it's a matmul.
And then you apply
a ReLU activation.
So this is not completely
out of nowhere.
But I'll show you
later why I did this.
OK, so how do you
build a matmul kernel?
All right, so here's
a naive approach.
OK, so here's my,
let's say, a matrix.
I'm multiplying A
times B. And I'm
trying to write out the matrix
C. And A is M by K, B is K by N.
So C is M by N. OK, so
what I'm going to do
is I'm going to fix
one of these elements.
Let's say M equals
1, N equals 2.
OK, so I'm processing--
actually, let's do M equals 1,
N equals 1.
So I'm doing C5.
And then, basically for every
k, so I'm going to, yeah,
I'm going to iterate
over the k, the rows of A
and the columns of B. I'm
going to read from HBM.
I'm going to multiply
them, accumulate that.
And at the end, I'm
going to write out
to this and this element.
So that is a valid
matmul kernel.
OK.
So what's wrong with it?
It's correct.
But if you look at how many
reads and writes it's doing,
this is not good.
Right, so basically for
every M and N and K,
I have to read from HBM.
So it's on the order of
M times K times N reads.
Number of writes.
I mean, it doesn't matter, but
this is the bottleneck, right.
And if you remember
from the second lecture,
if you look at the
number of operations
you're doing divided by
the number of bytes that
were transferred, that's
the arithmetic intensity
which you want to be high.
So the number of operations
is M times K times N order.
And then the number of
reads is also the same.
So arithmetic intensity is a
constant, which is not good.
OK, so if you look
carefully, you
notice that there is a
lot of redundant reads.
So imagine computing C4.
You needed to read
A4, A5, and A6.
And if you compute
C5, you're going
to have to read those
over again as well.
So if you can just
read those once,
then you really save on
reads, and that's great.
So let's try to use
shared memory to do that.
So here's the
idealized approach.
I'm going to load all of A
and B into shared memory.
And then I'm going
to just compute C. So
if I can do that, then I get--
now I don't have this
cubic number of reads,
I only get quadratic
number of reads,
which means I get the error
intensity of order n, which
in the second lecture, I said
was a kind of ideal thing
you could hope for.
OK, so if you can
do that, that's
great, because you basically--
there's no redundant reads.
You read everything
once into shared memory.
You do the computation
and you write it back.
OK, but what's the problem
with this idealized approach.
The problem is that
A and B are usually
too large to fit
into shared memory.
Right.
So then, what do
you have to do now?
OK, so the idea here is this
very classic idea of tiling.
And the idea basically
is to, well, fit as much
as you can to shared memory
as you can, essentially.
So in some sense,
it's going to look
like the naive-- it's going to
globally look like the naive
approach, but locally it look
like the idealized approach
is the way to think about it.
So here's the picture.
I think Tatsu
showed this as well.
So what we're going
to do is we're
going to take this matrix
C, and instead-- remember,
the naive approach just
said for every element,
I'm going to compute it.
But now I'm going to say for
every tile, I'm going to do it.
So I break it up into tiles.
And each of these tiles is
going to be a thread block.
And I'm going to have a
bunch of threads that is
responsible for computing this.
Now a different
tile is going to be
computed completely separately
by another thread block.
OK, so I'm going to--
imagine I'm in Triton.
I wake up.
I'm looking at
this thread block.
So what do I have to do?
Well, in some
sense, it's the same
as the naive approach where,
for every row tile of A,
I'm going to go scan
across the rows.
And for every column
tile of B, I'm
going to load the corresponding
tile A and the corresponding--
so say I'm here-- and
the corresponding tile
from B into shared memory.
I'm going to multiply
these two together.
And that's going to be like
the idealized approach.
And I'm going to accumulate
that in the partial sum.
And this is all sitting
in shared memory.
And then after I finish all the
sweep of the row and the column
here, then I can finally
write this output tile to HBM.
OK, so that's the
conceptually what's happening.
And then the arithmetic
intensity here
now goes up to order tile size.
So you can generally
not reach order n,
because that would require
you to fit everything
into shared memory.
But if your tiles are big,
then that's still not too bad.
OK, so just as a bonus.
While you're doing all
writing a kernel for this
anyway, sometimes if you want to
apply an element-wise activation
function, it's very easy to
just put it on at the end.
And this is kernel fusion.
OK, so very quickly,
the implementation here.
So-- oops.
OK, so just a reminder
about strides since this
is going to show up.
So a tensor is a
multidimensional array.
But in memory, it's linearized.
And strides of a tensor
tells you basically
how to map from a
multidimensional index
such as a row, a column,
into an actual index.
And basically what you
do is multiply the row
by the stride, the
plus the column
by the stride of the column.
OK, so in this case, every time
you go advance to the next row,
you go four positions
in your memory.
And every time you advance
a column, you go one.
And if it were to transpose,
it would be flipped.
OK, so what does this
kernel look like here?
OK, so the launch
is not interesting.
So you wake up and you
are on tile M and N.
So it's like OK, I'm responsible
for computing the c matrix,
but for the M comma
N tile there's
a bunch of index
manipulation which you can--
I'll just gloss through,
but it's straightforward
but a little bit.
You just have to
track the indices.
So this basically tells you
which rows of A, the matrix A,
I'm looking at.
Which rows of-- oh sorry, which
columns of B I'm looking at.
And then this is just
the numbers 1 through K.
Then I'm going to get
the pointers into A and B
at my tile location.
And then I'm going to set
up this accumulator matrix.
This is going to be
in shared memory.
It's M by N. And
then this is going
to look like the row
reduction, right.
You have this sum
over all the tiles.
But instead of just
going across the tiles,
I'm now going
across the row tiles
and also simultaneously
down the column
tiles of B. I load A, the small
matrix, I load B, the small B
tile.
And then I perform this dot.
So remember, whenever
things are in shared memory,
things look like PyTorch and
I can just say, matmul it,
and it will do the thing.
And then I advance to
the next row tile of A
and the next column tile of B.
The bonus is that
if I wanted to apply
element-wise non-linearity,
I might as well do that here.
Before I write it out to HBM, I
can do some any operation on it.
And then finally, I
just write it out.
OK, so there's some indices that
you have to pay attention to.
But hopefully, the form
of the algorithm is clear.
OK.
Any questions about that?
All right.
Maybe I'll just summarize,
and you can ask me later.
So today, we talked
about there's
a programming model,
which is you're
talking about either
PyTorch or Triton or ptx.
This is what the kind of
programmer can control.
Right, and even ptx.
You can write ptx and you can
control every-- specialize
however you want.
But this is not
the full picture,
because the reality is that your
code has to run on hardware,
and there's only a
finite number of SMs,
a finite number of banks, and
sizing of memory and registers.
All are finite.
So you come in with your
big matrix and transformer,
and want to-- it has to
fit in with the constraints
of the hardware.
So that's why
benchmarking and profiling
are really important
to understand
how the messiness
of the hardware
translates to performance.
We talked about
Triton, which is,
I think, a pretty nice,
neat language to think
about thread blocks.
Hopefully by now
you can appreciate
that things are easier to
think about thread blocks
than individual threads,
because you don't have
to think about explicitly
synchronizing threads or doing
shared memory.
And the way to think about it
is that you figure out-- you
have your computation.
You break it down
into the thread
blocks where you just need
to read from shared memory.
Do some stuff, and
write it back into HBM.
And then we saw some examples
of increasing difficulty.
Element wise is the easiest.
And then reduction over a row.
Reduction where it
doesn't fit into a row.
And we introduced
the baby tiling.
And then matmul is
the canonical example
where you actually do tiling.
OK, so that's all I'm
going to say about how
to program a single GPU.
Next time, we're going to
go to more GPU and talk
about multi-GPU programming.
Yeah, question.
So if I want to
write down kernels,
what are the alternatives?
Do I have to try them and--
for each of my
choices that I have,
how close can I get
to the optimal level?
So the question is, what
are alternatives to Triton?
So there's a trade off between--
every language has an
inductive bias, right.
That makes certain things easier
and certain things harder.
So most of what we do--
Triton was built by people
who train transformers.
So anything involving
transformers,
I think it's going to be
relatively easy there.
Of course, in the
extreme, you can always
go to ptx and write that.
But I wouldn't advise
that as a first step.
There are a bunch
of other libraries.
There's thunder kittens.
There's cute,
delirious DSLs that
allow you to give you-- they're
not necessarily comparable
either up or down the stack.
They just give you
different characteristics.
Yeah?
Do you have a high dimensional
tensor magnification
or high dimensional
tensor processing?
What is the best approach?
What I'm thinking is can I load
unload the whole sensor, both
of the sensors on bunch of
threads or thread blocks
on my GPU at the same
time and compute them?
Or would it be better
to take each element,
just what we did here, right.
A particular component
of my sensor,
then process it and then
write it back in the end.
Yeah, so briefly, the question--
and we should probably wrap up--
is, is it better
to read all at once
or maybe process individual
elements at a time?
I think it's hard to answer
this in the abstract.
It depends on the nature
of the computation.
Maybe we can talk
offline about that.
OK, all right.
See you next time.